What we want to talk about now is once the running back takes the hand off he first wants to go through the hole that he is assigned.
Every time in the huddle the running back will get an assignment of which hole he is supposed to go through.
Is he supposed to go through the three, is he supposed to go up the zero hole right behind the center, or is he supposed to go around the outside off tackle.
Once he has that assignment that's always his first option once he takes the ball.
However, sometimes, the linemen don't get their jobs done and that's to open up that hole.
Sometimes, if the running back's assignment was to go up the three hole and he finds out once he starts to step up and that three hole is closed.
He can't start dancing around and try to run outside and sweep around.
Usually, if this hole is not open he can usually find another one close by but he has to get the ball up field instead of stretching it out.
That's what the defense wants to do.
They want to get the running back to go as far outside as possible so they can make the tackle outside.
So, he has to make a decision, either he goes through the hole he's assigned or he tries to cut it back up inside on the left or right.
He has to make a quick decision.
The main thing is we want to get the ball north and south, not east and west.